<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><guidanceItem id="2ea277fd-8603-4906-a987-4ca5b8465436" type="checklist" title="Directory Browsing is Disabled" cssFile="guidance.css" Date="2010-09-21T15:36:41.515625Z" Author="" Category="Deployment Considerations" filePath="..\Libraries\OWASP\Checklist Item\2ea277fd-8603-4906-a987-4ca5b8465436.xml" Priority="2" Rule_Type="Deployment" Source="SI" Status="" Technology="ASP.NET 3.5" Topic="Security" Type="Checklist Item" xmlns="urn:microsoft:guidanceexplorer:guidanceItem"><content><![CDATA[<H1>What to Check For</H1><P>Ensure that directory browsing for your application's IIS directory is disabled.</P><H1>Why</H1><P>Directory browsing allows an attacker to browse your application's directory structure in search of unprotected files and components.</P><H1>How to Check</H1><P>Take the following steps to determine if directory browsing is disabled:</P><OL><LI>Open the IIS management utility. <LI>Navigate to your application's directory. <LI>Right click and select <STRONG>Properties</STRONG>. <LI>Navigate to the <STRONG>Directory</STRONG> tab. <LI>Verify that the <STRONG>Directory Browsing</STRONG> checkbox is <STRONG>not checked</STRONG>. <LI>Click <STRONG>OK</STRONG>.</LI></OL><H1>Problem Example</H1><P>An application is deployed on a production server. Unfortunately, the developers did not disable directory browsing. Directory browsing reveals critical clues which can be used to determine what software is being used on the server and how it is configured. It enables attackers to search for and download unprotected configuration files, source code, libraries, or data files. After finding and decompiling a library the attacker was able to discover another weakness and compromise the server further. </P><H1>Additional Resources</H1><LI>To learn more about setting web site permissions, including directory browsing, see <A href="http://technet2.microsoft.com/windowsserver/en/library/ede1f294-1dfd-4af8-8a38-d03f252c13431033.mspx?mfr=true">Configure Web Site Permissions in IIS6</A> <H1>Related Guideline</H1><UL><LI><A href="ruledisplay:EB8D8FDB-1AEB-4923-A8F3-8FF7D90B6B5A">Guideline: Disable Directory Browsing&nbsp;</A> </LI></UL><HR><P>Adapted from Microsoft patterns &amp; practices guidance. </P></LI>
]]></content></guidanceItem>