<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><guidanceItem id="ad75cecc-a8d1-46c9-a6ac-9bad61328e80" type="checklist" title="Application Does Not Rely Only on Client-Side Validation" cssFile="guidance.css" Date="2010-10-03T03:21:12.265625Z" Author="" Category="Input and Data Validation" filePath="..\Libraries\OWASP\Checklist Item\ad75cecc-a8d1-46c9-a6ac-9bad61328e80.xml" Priority="2" Rule_Type="Implementation" Source="SI" status="" Status="" Technology="ASP.NET 3.5" Topic="Security" Type="Checklist Item" xmlns="urn:microsoft:guidanceexplorer:guidanceItem"><content><![CDATA[<H1>What to Check For</H1><P>Ensure that your application is not relying on client-side validation in order to make security decisions.&nbsp;Client-side validation is ok to give the user feedback on bad input for a better user experience, but it can be easily bypassed, so you need to&nbsp;verify that&nbsp;all validation that occurs on the client also occurs on the server. </P><H1>Why</H1><P>Client-side validation can be easily bypassed. For example, a malicious user could disable&nbsp;the client-side script routines by disabling JavaScript. Users&nbsp;may also construct their own&nbsp;form posts using custom HTML, or&nbsp;using an&nbsp;HTTP proxy to modify form posts. Reliance on client-side validation can lead to code injection vulnerabilities (such as cross site scripting or SQL injection).&nbsp;If you use client-side validation to enforce application logic, such as the cost of items in an online store, the logic can be circumvented resulting in vulnerabilities ranging from application defacement to theft of merchandise or money. </P><H1>How to Check</H1><P>To check for this problem, use the following steps:&nbsp;</P><OL><LI><P><STRONG>Find all validation routines in your application.</STRONG> Review your application design and code for the presence of validation routines. Make a list of these for use in later steps. Every source of user input should be validated with a validation routine shortly after the input enters the application</P><LI><P><STRONG>Review the validation routines to ensure they run on the server. </STRONG>Review each validation routine and if it is client-side, ensure that it either has a corollary on the server or is designed to run on both client and server. For instance the ASP.NET validator controls, such as the <STRONG>RegularExpressionValidator</STRONG>, <STRONG>RangeValidator</STRONG>, and <STRONG>CustomValidator</STRONG>, will automatically validate input on both the client and the server</P></LI></OL><H1>How to Fix</H1><P>Validating input is&nbsp;inherently difficult because the range of&nbsp;possible&nbsp;values is hard to constrain. It is&nbsp;important to specify what input is acceptable rather than trying to specify all&nbsp;the&nbsp;variations&nbsp;of input that are&nbsp;illegal (allow listing as opposed to blacklisting).</P><P>Use ASP.NET validator controls to check user input on the server side and provide feedback to the user when input fails to pass validation requirements. Follow these steps on each form page in an application:</P><OL><LI><P><STRONG>Determine the required fields. </STRONG>Use the required field validator control to ensure all required fields are present. Here is an example that declares a text field in an ASP page that is a required field:</P><PRE>&lt;td&gt;<BR>&nbsp;&nbsp; &lt;asp:RequiredFieldValidator runat=server <BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; ControlToValidate=txtName<BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; ErrorMessage="User ID is required."&gt; &#42;<BR>&nbsp;&nbsp; &lt;/asp:RequiredFieldValidator&gt;<BR>&lt;/td&gt;<BR>&lt;td&gt;User ID:&lt;/td&gt;<BR>&lt;td&gt;&lt;input type=text runat=server id=txtName&gt;&lt;/td&gt;</PRE><P>The &#42; is displayed next to the label if the input is blank. The error message is reported in a summary. The <STRONG>ControlToValidate</STRONG> property specifies the ID of the control to validate. The final step is to add a validation summary to the top of the page like so:</P><PRE>&lt;asp:ValidationSummary runat=server <BR>HeaderText="There were errors on the page:" /&gt;<BR></PRE><LI><P><STRONG>Enforce numeric range&nbsp;constraints.&nbsp; </STRONG>Use the RangeValidator control to ensure any numeric values are constrained to a specific, acceptable&nbsp;range. Here is an example that declares an integer field&nbsp;in an ASP page that has&nbsp;a valid range from 1 to 50: </P><PRE>&lt;td&gt;<BR>  &lt;asp:RangeValidator id="Range1"<BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; ControlToValidate="txtState"<BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; MinimumValue="1"<BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; MaximumValue="50"<BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Type="Integer"<BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; EnableClientScript="false"<BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Text="The value must be from 1 to 50&#33;"<BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; runat="server"&gt; &#42; </PRE><PRE>&nbsp; &lt;/asp:RangeValidator&gt;<BR>&lt;/td&gt;<BR>&lt;td&gt;State:&lt;/td&gt;<BR>&lt;td&gt;&lt;input type=text runat=server id=txtState&gt;&lt;/td&gt;</PRE><LI><P><STRONG>Validate&nbsp;verification fields.&nbsp;</STRONG>Fields such as password entry are often verified by having the user re-type them to ensure they are correct. Use the <STRONG>CompareValidator</STRONG> control to make the comparisons and ensure validity/integrity. Here is an example that declares&nbsp;two password&nbsp;fields&nbsp;in an ASP page that&nbsp;must match in order to validate properly:</P><PRE>&lt;asp:CompareValidator runat=server<BR>            ControlToValidate=txtRePWord<BR>            ControlToCompare=txtPWord<BR>             ErrorMessage="Passwords do not match." /&gt;</PRE><P>In this case, the two fields being compared are "txtPWord" and "txtRePWord". If they do not&nbsp;match, validation fails with the error message, "Passwords do not match."</P><LI><P><STRONG>Enforce type constraints on string fields. </STRONG>String fields are the most difficult type of input to effectively validate because the range of acceptable&nbsp;characters is much larger then numeric&nbsp;and enumerated types. Regular expressions provide a flexible mechanism for dictating valid patterns and characters. Use the <STRONG>RegularExpressionValidator</STRONG> to perform a variety of checks on string-based fields such as zip codes and phone numbers.</P><P>Here is an example that declares a&nbsp;text field&nbsp;in an ASP page that should represent a five digit zip code consisting entirely of numeric digits, and a validator to enforce those constraints:</P><PRE>&lt;input type=text runat=server id=txtZip&gt;<BR>      &lt;asp:RegularExpressionValidator runat=server<BR>             ControlToValidate="txtZip"<BR>             ErrorMessage="Zip code must be 5 digits, all numbers."<BR>             ValidationExpression="&#91;0-9&#93;&#123;5&#125;"&gt; &#42;<BR>      &lt;/asp:RegularExpressionValidator&gt;<BR>&lt;td&gt;Zip code:&lt;/td&gt;<BR>&lt;td&gt;&lt;input type=text runat=server id=txtZip&gt;&lt;/td&gt;</PRE><LI><P><STRONG>Use custom validation to handle remaining&nbsp;input constraints. </STRONG>The built-in ASP.NET&nbsp;validation controls handle&nbsp;most of the cases that commonly arise in&nbsp;web applications, but there&nbsp;may be&nbsp;times when they are not appropriate.&nbsp;The <STRONG>CustomValidator</STRONG> enables custom validation code that can plug into the existing validation system. Here is an example that declares a&nbsp;text field&nbsp;in an ASP page. For this particular text field, there is business logic that needs to be satisfied which is not easily constrainable by the&nbsp;other&nbsp;validation constructs, so a&nbsp;custom validator is implemented that ensures the&nbsp;string&nbsp;in the text field&nbsp;does not start&nbsp;with the letter "a":</P><PRE>&lt;&#37;&#64; Page Language="vb" &#37;&gt;<BR> <BR>&lt;script runat=server&gt;<BR>public sub CheckID(source as Object, args as ServerValidateEventArgs)<BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; args.IsValid = args.Value.substring(0, 1).tolower() &lt;&gt; "a"<BR>end sub <BR> <BR>&lt;/script&gt;</PRE><P>To call this function, add a <STRONG>CustomValidator</STRONG>, which is designed to call developer code to perform its check. Here is the declaration:</P><PRE>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &lt;asp:CustomValidator runat=server<BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; controltovalidate="txtName" <BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; errormessage="ID is already in use." <BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; OnServerValidate="CheckID" /&gt;</PRE><P>It is worth noting that this could have been done with the <STRONG>RegularExpression</STRONG> validation control, but in this case it makes more sense to use custom validation since&nbsp;a type of high-level validation that could conceivably be more complex then a simple pattern match is being defined (e.g., the validation rules might change based on application state).&nbsp;</P></LI></OL></LI><OL></OL><H1>Problem Example</H1><P>Consider a very simple form for an online shopping cart. The cart component consists of two components:</P><OL><LI><P>An HTML form that contains all of the fields that make up the order to be submitted for processing:</P><BLOCKQUOTE><BLOCKQUOTE><PRE>&lt;html&gt;<BR>  &lt;head&gt;<BR>    &lt;title&gt;Widget shopping cart&lt;/title&gt;<BR>  &lt;/head&gt;<BR>  &lt;body&gt;<BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;  &lt;H1&gt;welcome to the most boring shopping cart on the web&#33;&lt;/H1&gt; </PRE><PRE>    A widget's current price is &#36;19.95 USD. Please use the following form to submit an order.</PRE><PRE>    &lt;form action="process_order.aspx" method="POST"&gt;  <BR>      &lt;p&gt;Please enter the number of widgets you would like to purchase:&lt;/p&gt;<BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;   quantity:&lt;br/&gt;<BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;  &nbsp;&lt;select name="WidgetQuantity"&gt;<BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;  &nbsp; &lt;option value="1"&gt;1&lt;/option&gt;<BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;   &lt;option value="2"&gt;2&lt;/option&gt; <BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;   &lt;option value="3"&gt;3&lt;/option&gt;<BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;   &lt;option value="4"&gt;4&lt;/option&gt;<BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;  &lt;/select&gt;</PRE><PRE>      ...<BR>      &lt;input type="submit" value="order"/&gt;<BR>    &lt;/form&gt;</PRE><PRE>  &lt;/body&gt;<BR>&lt;/html&gt;</PRE></BLOCKQUOTE></BLOCKQUOTE><LI><P>An ASP.NET page that processes the form submissions and performs the necessary steps to create the order.</P><BLOCKQUOTE><BLOCKQUOTE><PRE>int&nbsp;dQuantity = Request("WidgetQuantity");<BR>double dPrice = 19.95;</PRE><PRE>double dCost = dQuantity &#42; dPrice;</PRE></BLOCKQUOTE></BLOCKQUOTE></LI></OL><P>This server side page is problematic because it lacks validation to ensure the quantity field is correct.&nbsp;The application&nbsp;works fine in the case where a user plays by the rules and submits the form as it is shown because the&nbsp;quantity field ensures that the range constraints for the order quantity are always valid.&nbsp;However, if a clever user decides to construct their own form and submits a negative WidgetQuantity field, it causes a negative balance. Depending on what e-commerce system is used, this could result in a credit to the user's account. It also&nbsp;might subtract the negative balance from the company's inventory, which would carry significant ramifications and costs&nbsp;later on.</P><H1>Solution Example</H1><P>Consider the following ASP.NET page that processes the form submissions and performs the necessary steps to create an order:</P><PRE>&lt;&#37;&#64; Page Language="vb" &#37;&gt;<BR>&lt;script runat=server&gt;<BR>public sub OnSubmit(source as Object, e as EventArgs)<BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; if Page.IsValid then<BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; ' Now we can perform our transaction.<BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; int dQuantity = Request("WidgetQuantity");<BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; double dPrice = 19.95;<BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; double dCost = dQuantity &#42; dPrice;<BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; end if<BR>end sub<BR>&lt;/script&gt;<BR>&lt;html&gt;<BR>&lt;head&gt;<BR>&lt;title&gt;Validation Sample&lt;/title&gt;<BR>&lt;/head&gt;<BR>&lt;body&gt;</PRE><PRE>&lt;form runat=server&gt;<BR>&lt;asp:ValidationSummary runat=server headertext="There were errors on the page:" /&gt;</PRE><PRE>&lt;table&gt;<BR>&nbsp; &lt;tr&gt;<BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &lt;td&gt;<BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &lt;asp:RequiredFieldValidator runat=server <BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; controltovalidate="WidgetQuantity"<BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; errormessage="WidgetQuantity is required."&gt;&#42;<BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &lt;/asp:RequiredFieldValidator&gt;<BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &lt;/td&gt;<BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &lt;td&gt;A widget's current price is &#36;19.95 USD. Please use the following form to submit an order.&lt;/td&gt;<BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &lt;td&gt;<BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &lt;select name="WidgetQuantity"&gt;<BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &lt;option value="1"&gt;1&lt;/option&gt;<BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &lt;option value="2"&gt;2&lt;/option&gt;<BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &lt;option value="3"&gt;3&lt;/option&gt;<BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &lt;option value="4"&gt;4&lt;/option&gt;<BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &lt;/select&gt;<BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &lt;asp:RegularExpressionValidator runat=server display=dynamic<BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; controltovalidate="WidgetQuantity"&nbsp; <BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; errormessage="WidgetQuantity must be a non-zero, positive integer." <BR>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; validationexpression="&#91;1-9&#93;&#123;1&#125;&#91;0-9&#93;&#123;0,7&#125;" /&gt;</PRE><PRE>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &lt;/td&gt;<BR>&nbsp; &lt;/tr&gt;<BR>...<BR>&lt;/table&gt;&lt;br&gt;<BR></PRE><PRE>&lt;input type=submit runat=server id=cmdSubmit value=Submit onserverclick=OnSubmit&gt;<BR>&lt;/form&gt;<BR>&lt;/body&gt;<BR>&lt;/html&gt;</PRE><P>The ASP.NET Validator control provides client-side validation to reduce roundtrips to the server and improve user experience, but also provides server-side validation to&nbsp;ensure that the widget quantity field is&nbsp;a positive integer. It is also validated as a required field that must be provided before submitting the order.</P><H1>Additional Resources</H1><UL><LI>For more information on user input validation in ASP.NET, see User Input Validation in ASP.NET in MSDN.&nbsp;<A href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/library/default.asp?url=/library/en-us/dnaspp/html/pdc_userinput.asp">http://msdn.microsoft.com/library/default.asp?url=/library/en-us/dnaspp/html/pdc_userinput.asp</A>&nbsp; <LI>For more information on validation server control syntax, see Validation Server Control Index in MSDN.&nbsp;<A href="http://msdn2.microsoft.com/en-us/library/e5a8xz39.aspx">http://msdn2.microsoft.com/en-us/library/e5a8xz39.aspx</A> <LI>For more information on general purpose code injection, see Code injection in Wikipedia.&nbsp;<A href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Code_injection">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Code_injection</A>&nbsp; </LI></UL><H1>Related Items</H1><UL><LI><A href="ruledisplay:8ef52996-aec5-4274-aec1-85a3a313e0bc">Do Not Rely on Client-side Validation</A></LI></UL><HR><P>Adapted from Microsoft patterns &amp; practices guidance. </P>
]]></content></guidanceItem>